A Finding Aid to the Percy Leason Papers, circa 1929-2011, in the Archives of American Art AAA.leasperc
Archives of American Art
Percy Leason papers
circa 1929-2011
AAA.leasperc
Archives of American Art
1.3 Linear feet
The papers of painter, illustrator, and educator Percy Leason measure 1.3 linear feet and date from circa 1929 to 2011. The collection documents his career through biographical material, correspondence, diaries, writings and notes, printed material, photographic material, and a scrapbook.
Leason, Percy
Biographical/Historical note
Percy Leason (1889-1959) was a painter, illustrator, writer, and educator from Kaniva, Victoria in Australia. Leason took an interest in art at an early age winning first prize in painting at the 1904 State Fair. He later attended art school in the town of Nhill, and in 1906, he went to Melbourne to be an apprentice at Sands and McDougall Lithographers. Soon after starting his apprenticeship, Leason moved to the art department where he began drawing illustrations for products and advertisements. In the evenings, he attended the Melbourne Gallery School where he studied art under Bernard Hall and Frederick McCubbin. While in Melbourne, Leason associated himself with the Victorian Artist Society and lived a bohemian lifestyle. He began creating illustrations for books in 1914 and went on to do illustrations for the Sydney Bulletin, Melbourne Punch, Tabletalk Magazine, and the Melbourne Herald where he developed the Wiregrass cartoon series. In 1924, Leason and Max Meldrum, who Leason had met a few years before, discussed tonal realism, a systematic style of painting that uses light and shade to produce a misty quality. Leason's devotion to tonal realism along with his participation in Victorian Artist Society exhibitions helped advance his career. In 1934 Melbourne University commissioned him to do a series on Australian aborigines. He became interested in cave art and archeology during this time. In Cambridge, England in 1937 he presented his theory that cave artists sketched using dead animals as models.
Due to the impending World War, art scene rivalries, and the lack of commercial art employment prospects, Leason immigrated to New York in 1938 in search of more opportunities in the United States. Before emigrating to the U.S., he completed a portrait of Basil Burdett which now hangs in the Queensland Art Gallery in Brisbane, Australia. His career in New York included work for New York Daily News, Blue Book Magazine, the Saturday Evening Post, Street and Smith, and book illustrations for The Wizard of Oz by Frank Baum (Whitman Publishing Company) in 1939. In New York, Leason continued his opposition to modernist and expressionist art by aligning himself with the Salmagundi Club, Allied Artists, and the American Artist Professional League, all of which supported tonal realism. In association with Portraits Incorporated in New York, he painted the portraits of TV personality Arlene Francis, Michael Engel of Grumbacker art supplies, and Missouri congressman Dewey Short whose portrait is housed in the House of Representative’s collection in Washington D.C.
By the late 1950's, Leason had difficulties within the art world because the trends in art no longer held a place for his tonal realism. He died in 1959 on Staten Island in New York. As a tribute to Leason after his death, the Staten Island Institute and the Salmagundi Club held retrospective exhibitions of his work.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter, illustrator, and educator Percy Leason measure 1.3 linear feet and date from circa 1929 to 2011. The collection documents his career through biographical material, correspondence, diaries, writings and notes, printed material, photographic material, and a scrapbook.
Biographical materials include financial records, biographical statements about the artist, certificates, and a few sketches. Correspondence contains letters and writings of Max Leason, Percy Leason's son, correspondence to and from Percy Leason, letters from congressmen, and letters regarding Leason's work displayed at the State Library of Victoria in Australia. Four diaries document Leason's life over 20 years. A series of published and unpublished writings and notes includes two DVDs of Leason's writings. Printed material contains new clippings, gallery flyers, a framed statement about art, and the book The Science of Appearances by Max Meldrum with typed pages written by Leason inserted into the book. Photographic materials include slides and a DVD of Leason's artwork, personal photographs, and photographs of the State Library of Victoria. One scrapbook contains mostly news clippings and other printed material.
Scattered throughout the collection are annotations made by Max Leason which are usually signed "Max" with the date of annotation.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated in 1969-1979 and 2014 by Max A. Leason, Percy Leason's son.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1939-1957, 2006 (5 folders; Box 1, 2)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1946-1973 (4 folders, Box 1)
Series 3: Diaries, 1938-1959 (0.3 linear ft.; Box 1)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, 1939-2011 (6 folders, Box 1)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1946-1973 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 6: Photographic Materials, circa 1969-1972 (0.2 linear ft.; Box 1, 2)
Series 7: Scrapbook, 1938-1972 (0.1 linear ft.; Box 2)
Leason, Max; Meldrum, Max, 1875-1955; State Library of Victoria.; Diaries; Illustrators--New York (State)--Staten Island; Painters--New York (State)--Staten Island; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketches
- Biographical Material, 1939-1957; 2006; Series 1; 5 Folders Box 1, 2
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes an account book, account ledger, biographical statement written by Max Leason, Percy Leason's son, for AskArt.com, and certificates awarded by the Salmagundi Club, the Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences, and the Audubon Artists. Also included are six small sketches of figures in historical costume and one sketch of a boat.
  - Account Book, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Account Ledger, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Statements, 2006; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sketches, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificates, 1947-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1946-1973; Series 2; 4 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence includes the letters and writings of Max Leason regarding Percy Leason's artwork, membership status, and manuscripts sent to and from printers, museums, and art related organizations. Also within Max Leason's correspondence is a curriculum vitae for Percy Leason. The correspondence of Percy Leason documents his efforts to have his manuscripts published and contains letters expressing his opinions on art. Also found in correspondence are two letters from the U.S. House of Representatives, sent after Leason's death, requesting portraits of John McCormack, Overton Brooks, and James E. Van Zandt. Correspondence with the State Library of Victoria regarding an inventory of Leason's work that was deposited at the library is also included in this series.
  - Correspondence and Writings of Max Leason Regarding Percy Leason, 1968-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence Sent and Received by Percy Leason, 1946-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters from U.S. Congressmen, 1959; 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The State Library of Victoria, circa 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Diaries, 1938-1959; Series 3; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  This series includes four diaries that span over 20 years. The diaries document Leason's daily activities and thoughts. This series may include letters and news clippings that are either loose or pasted into the diaries.
  - Diary, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Diary, circa 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Diary, 1950; 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Diary, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Writings and Notes, 1939-2011; Series 4; 6 Folders Box 1
  Found within this series are Leason's notes on A Brief History of Painting, Paleolithic Art, and The Science of Appearances. Also included are published works by Leason in the Proceedings of the Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences, The Artist, and Australia. "Artist of Modern Times: the Biography of Percy Leason" by Max Leason and "Experience in Painting: An Analysis of the Visual Impression as Applied to Painting" by Percy Leason, edited by Max Leason are on two DVDs found in this series.
  - "Artist of Modern Times: The Biography of Percy Leason" (2011) by Max Leason, 1 Electronic discs (DVD) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Experience in Painting: An Analysis of the Visual Impression as Applied to Painting" (2010) by Percy Leason, edited by Max Leason, 1 Electronic discs (DVD) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notes on "A Brief History of Painting", undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Notes on Paleolithic Art, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notes on "The Science of Appearances", circa 1950's (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Published Work, 1939-1962 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Printed Material, 1973; circa 1946-1973; Series 5; 4 Folders Box 1
  Printed material consists of news clippings about Max Meldrum, flyers from the Adams, Davidson Galleries, a framed statement about art, and a reporduction of the Dewey Short portrait by Leason with a printed program from the portrait's unveiling. The book by Max Meldrum, The Science of Appearances, has typed writings by Leason inserted into the book where Leason thought appropriate.
  - Adams, Davidson Galleries, Inc., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - News Clippings About Max Meldrum, circa 1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Framed Statement About Art, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Reproduction of Dewey Short Portrait, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Science of Apearances by Max Meldrum, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Photographic Materials, circa 1929-1970s; 2010; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1, 2
  Photographic materials contains 1 DVD of Leason's paintings, photographs and slides of Leason's artwork, and some personal photographs showing candid photographs of Leason, a photo of Arlene Francis with her portrait, and Leason at work. Photographs on the DVD, slides, and prints may be duplicates.
  - Photographs of Paintings, 2010; 1 Electronic discs (DVD) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Photographs of Artwork, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Photographs of Artwork, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Photographs, Personal, circa 1929-1950s (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Slides of Artwork, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Slides of Artwork, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - The State Library of Victoria, circa 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Scrapbook, 1938-1972; Series 7; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  The scrapbook contains mainly news clippings and other printed material documenting Leason's career in Australia and New York. A few pieces of correspondence and notes are also included.
  - Scrapbook, 1938-1972 (Box 2)